Guide to the O. Jack Mitchell architecture papers, 1960-1992 MS 439
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
O. Jack Mitchell architecture papers
1960-1992
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Mitchell, O. Jack
MS 439
7 Linear Feet (7 boxes and oversize material)
This collection contains the personal and academic papers of Houston architect O. Jack Mitchell. Included in the collection are Mitchell's consulting projects, Houston organizations projects, numerous slides of cities around the world, film reels of lectures, and various other architectural materials.
Biographical / Historical
O. Jack Mitchell (1931-1992) was a nationally recognized architectural expert and served as Dean of the School of Architecture at Rice University for eleven years. Before he was named Dean, he was also a professor of Architecture at Rice and Director of the School of Architecture as well. Mitchell received his Bachelor of Architecture degree from Washington University and his Master of City Planning and Master of Architecture from the University of Pennsylvania. Besides being a professor at Rice, he was also an Assistant Professor of Architecture at Texas A and M University from 1957-1959. He lectured at Auburn University, the University of Arkansas, Texas A and M, Louisiana State University, and the University of Houston. Mitchell had many articles published and was associated with several architectural firms in Houston. Mitchell was a member of many professional associations and served as a board member of the Rice Design Alliance and a chairman of the South Main Center Association.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the personal and academic papers of Houston architect O. Jack Mitchell. Included in the collection are Mitchell's consulting projects, Houston organizations projects, numerous slides of cities around the world, film reels of lectures, and various other architectural materials.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to Fondren by O. Jack Mitchell's estate on August 4, 1992.
Index Terms
Subjects
Architecture; Architects -- Texas; Universities and colleges
Document Types
speeches; letters (correspondence); architectural drawings (visual works); photographs; videotapes; slides (photographs); audiotapes
Subjects (Persons)
Mitchell, Carolyn E. (Mrs. O. Jack)
- Series I. Correspondence and speeches, 1960-1988; 38044; Mitchell, O. Jack; 0 Linear Feet
  Mitchell, Carolyn E. (Mrs. O. Jack)
  - Personal Correspondence 1967-1988, 40417 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Postcards, 40418 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia and Biographical info, 40419 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Course work, papers 1960-61, 40420 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jury Week Projects (Arkansas), 40421 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Institute Lecture, 40422 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Houston Lectures, 40423 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles, 40424 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speech Notes, 40425 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Talks, 40426 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Information related to lectures, 40427 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Duncan Plaza/New Orleans, 40428 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arch. Education – Arkansas, 40429 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Urban Design Conference January 1986, 40430 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Neighborhood lecture, 40431 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Consulting, 1963-1986; 40411
  - Jamiah Consortium Project Plaque August 1986, 40412 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Low-rent Public Housing Project Nov. 1965, 40432 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Southern State College Dormitories Aug 1963, 40433 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Central Arkansas Milk Producers Assoc. Office Building April 1965; Univ. of Arkansas Library and Arkansas Louisiana Gas Co. Office Building 1966, 40434 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Oak Grove Junior-Senior High School 1963, 40435 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Football Hall of Fame Competition 1967; "Understanding Urban Design: the Beginning" April 1966., 40436 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Moderate income housing project – downtown Houston, 40437 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Omniplan, 40438 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Omniplan UDP – Brochure, 40439 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Arkansas Gazette, 40440 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Housing Proposals, 40441 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Urban Design Proposals, 40442 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - New Communities Proposals, 40443 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cox – San Antonio, 40444 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Omniplan Proposals, 40445 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Omniplan UDP Announcement, 40446 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Omniplan Urban Design and Planning, 40447 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Champion Realty Corporation, 40448 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - General Portland Cement, 40449 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Land Development Planning Proposals, 40450 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series III: Organizations, 1980-1991; 40415
  - To do lists/McCommons visits, 40451 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dedication letters, 40452 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ACSA miscellaneous meetings, 40453 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Presidential schedule, 40454 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 40455 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - JAE, 40456 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1983 Teachers Seminar, 40457 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Auburn talk, 40458 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Key West/board meeting, 40459 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - JAE Information, 40460 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Institute of Architects (AIA), 40461 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - FAIA, 40462 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - AIA Houston, 40463 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - N.O. IDP Meeting Sept 1982, 40464 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - AIA, 40465 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Autry House, 40466 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Billboards, Ltd., 40467 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Friends of Sewall Gallery, 40468 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Grand Parkway Association, 40469 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Greater Houston Partnership, 40470 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Greater Houston Preservation Alliance (1 of 2), 40471 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Greater Houston Preservation Alliance (2 of 2), 40472 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Houston Parks Board, 40473 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Houston Public Library, 40474 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - National Architectural Accrediting Board (NAAB) Related, 40475 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - NAAB Report and Response, 40476 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - NAAB Correspondence, 40477 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - National Institute for Architectural Education (NIAE), 40478 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - NIAE Conference Transcript, 40479 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rice Center for Community Designand Research, 40480 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rice Design Alliance Debate 15 Oct 1985, 40481 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rice Design Alliance (1 of 2), 40482 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rice Design Alliance (2 of 2), 40483 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Trees for Houston, 40484 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - South Main Center Association (SMCA) Annual Meeting, 40485 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - SMCA Meeting Agendas 1989-1991 (1 of 2), 40486 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - SMCA Meeting Agendas 1989-1991 (2 of 2), 40487 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - SMCA General (1 of 4), 40488 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - SMCA General (2 of 4), 40489 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - SMCA General (3 of 4), 40490 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - SMCA General (4 of 4), 40491 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Contract, 40555 (Box 3, Item data_value_missing_a232a2e834a55c970fae733a23d8f07e)
  - Bush library (2f), 40556 (Box 3, Item data_value_missing_0160b0c07c0137a07cd39141099a64cd)
  - Bush library transparencies, 40557 (Box 3, Item data_value_missing_a3e57d8f39e1423254cb34d55621f44f)
  - George W. Bush Presidential Center Official Proposal, 40558 (Box 3, Item data_value_missing_1e829d4444808735c065936849541518)
- Series IV: Slides, undated; 40413
  - Corbusier, 40492 (Box 3)
  - The Moorish South - A.2, 40493 (Box 3)
  - Houston B UD Lecture, 40494 (Box 3)
  - Hoouston Miscellaneous, 40495 (Box 3)
  - Teoti…2, 40496 (Box 3)
  - FLLW, 40497 (Box 3)
  - Reston - Columbia, 40498 (Box 3)
  - Teoti…1, 40499 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous untitled 3, 40500 (Box 3)
  - The Moorish South A.3, 40501 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Untitled 1, 40502 (Box 3)
  - Teoti…Tikal, 40503 (Box 3)
  - Houston A Lecture, 40504 (Box 3)
  - PSM 2c (second tray), 40505 (Box 3)
  - Taxeo, 40506 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Untitled 2, 40507 (Box 3)
  - Sienna, 40508 (Box 3)
  - Chicago, 40509 (Box 3)
  - Empirical Analysis, 40510 (Box 3)
  - Berlin, 40511 (Box 3)
  - Tikal 1, 40512 (Box 3)
  - Tikal 2, 40513 (Box 3)
  - New Orleans Comp. 1, 40514 (Box 3)
  - Spanish steps, 40515 (Box 3)
  - Washington D.C. B, 40516 (Box 3)
  - Chicago Circle, 40517 (Box 3)
  - 2 sets of proposed Bush Library architectural drawings, 40518 (Drawer 27)
  - Al Khobar, 40519 (Box 4)
  - Sea Pines, Harbortown, South Beach, Sea Pines Statistics and Profiles, 40520 (Box 4)
  - Seattle: Pike Place Market, 40521 (Box 4)
  - Society Hill and Peabody Terrace, 40522 (Box 4)
  - Boston Government Center, 40523 (Box 4)
  - European City Plans, 40524 (Box 4)
  - Delphi, 40525 (Box 4)
  - American Design, 40526 (Box 4)
  - Athens: Agora and Acropolis, 40527 (Box 4)
  - The Moorish South – B.3, 40528 (Box 4)
  - The Moorish South – A.3, 40529 (Box 4)
  - Europe A UD Lecture, 40530 (Box 4)
  - Campi Doglio, 40531 (Box 4)
  - USA B UD Lecture, 40532 (Box 4)
  - The Moorish South – B.1, 40533 (Box 4)
  - The Moorish South – A.1, 40534 (Box 4)
  - Miami B UD Lecture, 40535 (Box 4)
  - U VA 1, 40536 (Box 4)
  - Scarborough College, 40537 (Box 4)
  - U VA 2, 40538 (Box 4)
  - Mykonos, 40539 (Box 4)
  - USA A UD Lecture, 40540 (Box 4)
  - Europe B UD Lecture, 40541 (Box 4)
  - Wash D.C. A, 40542 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, 40543 (Box 5)
  - Mont Saint Michel, 40544 (Box 5)
  - Chambers County New Community Group 1 and 2, 40545 (Box 5)
  - Chambers County New Community Group 4, 40546 (Box 5)
  - Sea Pines, General, Forest Preserve, Housing Types, 40547 (Box 5)
  - Piazza San Marco, 40548 (Box 5)
  - Philadelphia Story, 40549 (Box 5)
  - Charleston, 40550 (Box 5)
  - Williamsburg, 40551 (Box 5)
  - Annapolis and Savannah, 40552 (Box 5)
  - Reston, 40553 (Box 5)
  - Columbia, 40554 (Box 5)
- Series V: Films, VHS and cassette tapes, 1968-1986; 40414
  - Caudill lecture "The Triad Theory" and Focht, Jr. lecture "Design and Construction of Major Building Foundations in Downtown Houston", 41003 (Box 5)
  - Jullian, 41004 (Box 5)
  - Dr. Fazlur Khkan "Systems Approach to Design of High Rise Buildings," 30 Oct 1968., 41005 (Box 5)
  - Caudill "The Triad Theory" (2), 41006 (Box 5)
  - Braden lecture "Evaluation of Total Municipal Water Demands for the City of Houston," Soltunski lecture "Architectural Education in South Africa," Sobel lecture"TV as a Design Tool", 41007 (Box 5)
  - Talbot Wilson 3 Feb 1969, 41008 (Box 5)
  - George Pierce 30 Sept 1968 Houston International Airport; Cummins 7 Oct 1968 Lighting Power Grid, 41009 (Box 5)
  - Bill Caudill "What is Architecture" 16 Sept 1968; Evans "Lighting" 23 Sept 1986, 41010 (Box 5)
  - George Nelson "Of the Object Future" 10 Dec 1986, 41011 (Box 5)
  - Felix Candella 25 Nov 1968, 41012 (Box 5)
  - President's Lecture, 41013 (Box 5)
  - ASL Judge Thomas J. Stovall "Most Architecture is Hereditary – like Children" 21 Oct 1968; ASL James Thomas "Interior Design" 28 Oct 1968., 41014 (Box 5)
  - ASL Prof. Anderson Todd "Leonardo da Vinci: Arch. and Planner" 18 Nov 1968; ASL S.B. Qisman "Open Space Planning" 2 Dec 1968, 41015 (Box 5)
  - Venturi Las Vegas II 21 Jan 1969; Venturi Architecture 22 Jan 1969, 41016 (Box 5)
  - Shelton, Ladatut and Jullian, 41017 (Box 5)
  - VHS tape: America by Design Part I, 41018 (Box 5)
  - VHS tape: America by Design Part II: The Workplace, 41019 (Box 5)
  - VHS tape: America by Design Part III: The Street, 41020 (Box 5)
  - Cassette tape: Conversations regarding the future of architecture, 41021 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified photos, 41022 (Box 5)
- Series VI: Projects and published materials, 1961-1987; 40416
  - Savannah Materials; 1961 and 1976, 41023 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Materials; 1967 and 1974, 41024 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Lee Estate Land Development Analysis; April 1971, 41025 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lecture Notes and Student Papers; 1971 and 1973, undated, 41026 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Champion Realty Property Analysis of Lake Maurepas, LA; April 1973, 41027 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 18th Century Annapolis – Savannah; circa 1975, 41028 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Book Citations and Mexican Bank Receipt; February 1976, undated, 41029 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Influence of the Foreign Heritage on the American City; October 1976, 41030 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Establishment of Rice Architecture Programs; 1976, 1979, 1980, undated, 41031 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Houston Materials; 1976, 1977, 1979, undated, 41032 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Washington, DC Tourism Booklet with Note; circa 1976, 41033 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Washington, DC Materials; 1977, 41034 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Dallas North Development Property: Preston Rd. at S.H. 121 Booklet; circa 1970's, 41035 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Site Analysis: Gifco Matthews Tract Booklet; circa 1970's, 41036 (Box 6, Drawer 14)
  - San Antonio Downtown Financial Center Booklet; circa 1970's, 41037 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Sabbatical at University of Texas, University of Pennsylvania, and Ohio State University; January – May 1980, 41038 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Progressive Architecture; June and July 1980, 41039 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - AIA Journal; July and August 1980, 41040 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Urban Design International with Article by Mitchell; July/August 1980, 41041 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Society of Architectural Historians' Little Journal; September 1981, 41042 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Taller de Arquitectura by Ricardo Bofill; 1981, 41043 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Michael Heizer – 45°, 90°, 180°: A Sculpture for Rice University; 1985, 41044 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Uptown Holiday Lighting and Sesquicentennial; 1986, 1987, 41045 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - William Caudill Booklet; circa 1980's, 41046 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Heart of the Park Design Competition (dedicated to Mitchell); May 26, 1992, 41047 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - San Antonio: Downtown Booklet; undated, 41048 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - 7 in. reel tape labeled "Blank Tape" and "Maya"; May 11, 1979 and April 20, 1980, 41049 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - The San Antonio River: Urban Design Issues Cassette Tapes; undated, 41050 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue; Report of the President's Temporary Commission on Pennsylvania Avenue; January 1969, 41051 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - New Orleans Duncan Plaza competition, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Grant applications, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Arkansas projects, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Oversize items in map case drawer 27., 41052 (Map-drawer 27)
- Series VII: Addendum, 1981-1992
  - Lectures: Building for the Public (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miami: Plan/UM Architecture (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Miami: Plan Charrette, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - University of Miami (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - U of Miami: Architecture Upper Level Studio, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Miami: Interviews (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miami: Hammocks Development (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Miami: Structure - Places (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Miami: Infrastructure (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Miami: Articles, papers (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Miami: Publications (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miami: Drawings (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - ACSA Election, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Friends of Hermann Park (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Rice Department of Architecture Dean Search (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Rice Alumni Assoc Travel to Russia, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Certificates (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Urban Design for the Gulfton Community, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 19)